{"tossups": [{"question": "At this battle, Congreve rockets fired into American forces caused confusion, leaving Joshua Barney\u2019s flotilla force of African-Americans on its own. Tobias Stansbury dug artillery earthworks on Lowndes Hill during this battle. William Winder\u2019s forces were defeated at this battle by Robert Ross. This battle\u2019s namesake \u201cRaces\u201d led to the need for Paul Jennings and Dolley Madison to save a presidential portrait. For ten points, name this 1814 victory for the British in Maryland that led to the burning of Washington, DC.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Bladensburg</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This polity took a more isolationist stance after the battle of Rio Salado, at which the Marinids were defeated. This polity\u2019s last ruler, Boabdil, went into an almost five decade exile in Fes. This polity\u2019s rulers were named after Muhammad I\u2019s ancestor, Nasr the Red, and \u201cred\u201d is the translation for this polity\u2019s best known work of architecture. This polity was ruled from the Alhambra and ended in 1492 after its conquest by Castile. For ten points, name this polity and city of southern Spain.", "answer": "Nasrid Emirate of<em><b> Granada</b></em> (accept Nasrid Kingdom of<em><b> Granada</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This author wrote a \u201cfuneral sermon\u201d that opens, \u201cWeep not, weep not, She is not dead.\u201d This author coined the term \u201cRed Summer\u201d to describe racial violence in 1919. The narrator of a novel by this author tours Europe with a benefactor while playing ragtime music, then moves to New York after viewing a brutal lynching. This author wrote a poem often considered the \u201cBlack National Anthem\u201d that includes,\u201cLift every voice and sing.\u201d For ten points, name this author of God\u2019s Trombones and Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man.", "answer": "James Weldon<em><b> Johnson</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This conflict included a surprise raid on Maaten el-Sarra, for which French forces were blamed despite not being involved. The French were, however, participants in this conflict as part of the larger Operation Epervier. Hissene Habre was given Stinger missiles by the US to use in this conflict. This conflict gets its name from the makeshift \u201cTechnicals\u201d employed by FANT and FAP guerrilla forces against Muammar Gaddafi\u2019s army. For ten points, name this war fought over control of the Aouzou Strip by Chad and Libya.", "answer": "Great<em><b> Toyota</b></em> War (prompt on the \u201cChadian-Libyan conflict\u201d or similar answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The site of a university created by Benedik Kischdy, this city was captured in 1938 by a country that called it \u201cKassa.\u201d A pact signed in this city in 1374 allowed a daughter of Louis I to gain the Polish throne upon the death of Casimir the Great. A government formed in this city in 1945 was led by prime ministers Zdenek Fierlinger and Klement Gottwald but only lasted for three years. Located near the eastern Slovak Ore Mountains, for ten points, name this second-largest city of Slovakia.", "answer": "<em><b> Kosice</b></em> [KOSH-it-suh] (accept<em><b> Kassa</b></em> before mentioned) Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A battle partly named for this cardinal number took place in Henrico County and included a costly victory by George McClellan against Joseph Johnston. This number names a series of clashes of which Daniel Harvey Hill said, \u201cIt wasn\u2019t war, it was murder,\u201d after the Battle of Malvern Hill. A battle also called \u201cFair Oaks\u201d includes this number and occurred a month before a series of battles with this number in which Robert E. Lee drove Union forces away from Richmond. For ten points, name this number of Days and Pines in these 1862 battles.", "answer": "<em><b> Seven</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Lack of government support was to blame for this battle\u2019s outcome according to Gary Bernsten, the head of the CIA\u2019s Jawbreaker team. Tommy Franks was blamed for not sealing off escape routes at this battle, allowing its target to flee to Parachinar. Delta operative Dalton Fury\u2019s account of this battle blames Pakistan\u2019s poor border security for its result. For ten points, name this December 2001 battle, named for a cave complex in Afghanistan\u2019s White Mountains, that failed to capture a fleeing Osama bin Laden.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Tora Bora</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "According to legend, when this man was killed in his tent by a warrior named Brodir, a boy was wounded by the same sword stroke that beheaded this man, but the boy\u2019s wound was immediately healed. This winner at the Battle of Balech Lechta was buried at Armagh after he died in April 1014. That battle was part of a rebellion that started while this man conquered Ulster. For ten points, name this ruler who died at the Battle of Clontarf after ruling for twelve years as High King of Ireland.", "answer": "<em><b> Brian</b></em> Boru (accept<em><b> Brian</b></em> Borumac Cennetig, accept<em><b> Brian</b></em> Boramha, accept<em><b> Brian </b></em>Boruma)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This film ends with its protagonist relating how, during Roman triumphs, slaves would whisper into a conquerors ear, \u201cThat all is fleeting.\u201d That protagonist of this film smiles smugly after another character realizes that the protagonist had arrived in Messina before him as part of the Allied invasion of Sicily. In this film, the protagonist claims, \u201cNo bastard ever won a war by dying for his country,\u201d in a speech given to the Third Army. Bernard Montgomery is a rival of the protagonist in, for ten points, what biographical film about a namesake U.S. general?", "answer": "<em><b> Patton</b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "The president of this organization\u2019s Chicago branch established the Bethesda Day Nursery. A leader of this organization discussed her \u201cDo Nothing\u201d policy in a speech given to the \u201cWhite Ribbon Army.\u201dMatilda Carse began this organization\u2019s journal, The Union Signal, and Carrie Nation started one of its chapters. Annie Wittenmeyer was the first president of, for ten points, what women\u2019s organization led by Frances Willard to promote prohibition?", "answer": "<em><b> Woman\u2019s Christian Temperance Union</b></em> (accept<em><b> WCTU</b></em> ) Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Students at this university protested the appointment of Jane Fernandes after the retirement of President Irving King Jordan. Students demanded the resignation of Jane Bassett Spilman and burned effigies of Elizabeth Zinser at this university during the DPN movement. This school\u2019s founder was inspired by Alice Cogswell, who suffered from \u201cspotted fever.\u201d For ten points, name this Washington, D.C. university where students took part in the Deaf President Now protests.", "answer": "<em><b> Gallaudet</b></em> University", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The losing side of this battle initially repulsed the winning side at Oberglau under Ferdinand de Marsin, but a successful crossing of the River Nebel caused the Bavarian army to retreat. At this battle, the Duc de Tallard was captured by the Grand Alliance forces of Eugene of Savoy and the Duke of Marlborough. For ten points, name this decisive 1704 battle during the War of the Spanish Succession, the namesake of a palace built for one of its victorious commanders.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Blenheim</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "After the overthrow of this country\u2019s prime minister, Timoci Bavadra, another country launched Operation Morris Dance. Following that 1987 coup, Sitiveni Rabuka declared this country a republic. Kamisese Mara is considered the founding father of this country, in which Mahendra Chaudhry was taken hostage by George Speight. This country, united by King Cakobau, elected Frank Bainimarama as prime minister in 2007. For ten points, name this Melanesian archipelagic nation.", "answer": "Republic of<em><b> Fiji</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Ida C. Craddock was arrested for violating this law by promoting the spiritual movement of Dianism. This law was passed in response to Victoria Woodhull and Tennessee Claflin\u2019s expose on Henry Ward Beecher. Margaret Sanger was arrested for violating this law after opening a birth control clinic in New York City, and its namesake was a special agent of the U.S. Postal Service. For ten points, what is this law, named for an anti-vice activist, that banned the passing of obscene materials through the mail?", "answer": "<em><b> Comstock</b></em> Law(s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This \u201cZola of the Occult\u201d abandoned a cycle of historic plays but did complete a story about Olaus Petri\u2019s struggle to free the Church of Sweden from Roman domination, Master Olof. This author related his struggles with mental illness in the autobiographical novel, Inferno. This author of A Dream Play and The Ghost Sonata wrote a play in which the protagonist commits suicide with a razor, Miss Julie. For ten points, name this author of The Red Room, considered the \u201cFather of modern Swedish literature.\u201d", "answer": "August<em><b> Strindberg</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "Anna Louise Strong relocated to this country after being expelled by a northern neighbor. Jack Belden reported on a conflict in this country, though he refused to conduct interviews with its leader in a cave. It\u2019s not India, but Douglas MacArthur accused Agnes Smedley of espionage following the publishing of her book, Battle Hymn of...[this country]. Red Star over...[this country] titles Edgar Snow\u2019s account of a campaign aided by communist journalist, Otto Braun. For ten points, name this Asian country.", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of<em><b> China</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Charles W. Morgan was built in this city that lies on Buzzard Bay. The toggling harpoon was invented in this city for its most famous industry. For ten points, name this Massachusetts city in which Hermann Melville worked as a whaler.", "answer": "<em><b> New Bedford</b></em>, Massachusetts", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, the 12th Infantry Regiment was decimated at the Battle of Sand Butte. A leader of one side in this war asked Edward Canby to \u201cgive us a home in our country\u201d before cutting his throat. This war opened at the Battle of Lost River, which began after the US Army forced a band of the namesake tribe back to the Klamath Reservation. Before his execution during this war, Kintpuash, known as \u201cCaptain Jack,\u201d fled to Lava Beds National Monument. For ten points, name this 1872-73 war in northeastern California.", "answer": "<em><b> Modoc</b></em> War (accept<em><b> Modoc</b></em> Campaign, accept<em><b> Lava Beds</b></em> War before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "According to the Bamboo Annals, this figure died during a hunting trip on Mount Kuaiji and was then buried in Shaoxing. During his reign, this figure divided his kingdom into nine zhou or provinces. This figure\u2019s wisdom impressed King Shun so much that he was made heir to the throne over Shun\u2019s own son. This figure helped his father, Gun, utilize growing soil to accomplish his most noted task. For ten points, name this likely legendary founder of the Xia dynasty, who stopped the flooding of the Yellow River.", "answer": "<em><b> Yu</b></em> the Great (accept Da<em><b> Yu</b></em>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This politician led a filibuster with Robert La Follette of the Armed Ship Bill in 1917. Other defiant stances by this man include his crossing of the aisle to support Al Smith in 1928. This politician announced changes to House rules on St. Patrick\u2019s Day in 1910 to oust tyrannical Speaker, (+) \u201cUncle Joe\u201d Cannon. This man was featured as one of the\u201cCourageous Eight\u201d in John F. Kennedy\u2019s Profiles in Courage for protesting US entry into World War One. This politician authored a bill outlawing (*)</b> \u201cyellow-dog\u201d contracts with Fiorello LaGuardia. For ten points, name this progressive senator from Nebraska.", "answer": "George William<em><b> Norris</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Plans for this event were initially laid out after the Four Days Battle. Upnor Castle and the Gillingham line failed to prevent this event, during which Unity was the first ship lost. Royal James and Royal Oak were burnt at Chatham dockyards during this event. The (+) Royal Charles was captured during this event, and its royal arms are on display at the Rijksmuseum. Johan De Witt masterminded this event, and (*)</b> Dutch forces during this event were commanded by Michel de Ruyter. For ten points, name this successful surprise attack by the Dutch on the English fleet which ended the Second Anglo-Dutch War.", "answer": "<em><b> Raid</b></em> on the<em><b> Medway</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The leader of the winning side at this battle swore he would take the Aruna road, through what is today known as the \u201cNorthern Triangle,\u201d as his \u201cnostrils [were] rejuvenated with life and satisfaction.\u201d The victors at this battle looted the countryside of the Jezreel Valley. Details about this battle came from the scribe Tjaneni and were recorded in the (+) Hall of Annals at the Temple of Amun. This battle was fought a year after its victor succeeded his stepmother Hatshepsut. The (*)</b> Canaanites and the King of Kadesh were defeated at this battle by Thutmose III. For ten points, name this 1457 BC battle.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Megiddo</b></em>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Historian John Paynter described Judson Diggs\u2019s role as a \u201cJudas\u201d in this event. Horace Mann served as a lawyer to those indicted in this event including Captain Daniel Drayton and Edward Sayres, who owned its namesake. The Salem was sent out by (+) slaveowners in this event and captured a ship at Point Lookout. Paul Jennings, a former slave to James Madison helped plan this event, and after it occurred, Henry Ward Beecher\u2019s church freed the (*) </b> Edmonson sisters. 77 people attempted escape in, for ten points, what 1848 incident in Washington, D.C, the largest non-violent slave escape attempt in America?", "answer": "<em><b> Pearl</b></em> Incident Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This poet claimed \u201cto live in mankind is far more than to live in a name\u201d in his elegy to John Altgeld, \u201cThe Eagle That is Forgotten.\u201d A \u201cbronzed, lank man\u201d in a \u201chigh top-hat\u201d is unable to sleep in one of this author\u2019s poems because \u201ctoo many peasants fight\u201d as he paces through (+) Springfield, Illinois. The refrain \u201cAre you washed in the blood of the lamb?\u201d is repeated in another of this man\u2019s poems about the death of the founder of the (*)</b> Salvation Army. For ten points, name this poet of \u201cAbraham Lincoln Walks at Midnight\u201d and \u201cGeneral William Booth Enters into Heaven.\u201d", "answer": "Vachel<em><b> Linsday</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b>This leader died on a mountain now named after him during the Siege of Panticapeum. This man eliminated his brother, Chrestus, and his mother, Laodice, to become sole heir to the throne. Pliny the Elder related that this man could speak the languages of (+) all 22 nations he governed. This man was defeated in a series of conflicts that pitted him against military leaders like Lucius Lucullus. Delphi\u2019s treasury was sacked by Lucius Cornelius Sulla in the first conflict against this one-time ruler of (*)</b> Asia Minor. For ten points, name this king of Pontus and formidable opponent of Rome.", "answer": "<em><b> Mithridates</b></em> VI Eupator (accept<em><b> Mithridates</b></em> the Great)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s wife, Hannah Wilkinson, became the first American woman to receive a patent. As a child, this man worked at Jedediah Strutt\u2019s operation which utilized a water frame. This man employed the \u201cRhode Island System\u201d for his operations and built The Old Green (+) Mill. With William Almy and Moses Brown, this man used Richard Arkwright\u2019s ideas to build a water-powered mill in Pawtucket. Name this (*)</b> \u201ctraitor\u201d to England who built, for ten points, the first water mills in the United States, a man whom Andrew Jackson called, the\u201cfather of the American Industrial Revolution.\u201d", "answer": "Samuel<em><b> Slater</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The hereditary fudai branch of these people was the origin of each of the \u201cFour Great Generals.\u201d The policy of sankin-kotai required these people to leave their han every other year to live in the capital. During the (+) Meiji Restoration the kuge merged with this class to form the kazoku. With a name translating to \u201clarge land,\u201d these people were forced to cut down on the size of their (*)</b> samurai armies under Tokugawa Ieyasu. For ten points, name these powerful Japanese feudal lords, second only to the shogun.", "answer": "<em><b> Daimyo</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man is depicted within a crowd witnessing a scene from Augustine\u2019s City of God in a painting he commissioned titled La Gloria. On the advice of Pietro Aretino, one portrait of this man alludes to St. George despite his being too (+) gout-stricken to ride a horse. An eagle carrying an olive branch flies over this man\u2019s head in a painting by Anthony van Dyck. In one portrait, this man is depicted emerging from a forest on horseback during a victory against the Schmalkaldic League. (*)</b> Titian painted a portrait of, for ten points, what Holy Roman Emperor \u201cat Muhlberg\u201d?", "answer": "<em><b> Charles V</b></em>, Holy Roman Emperor (accept<em><b> Carlos I</b></em>, accept<em><b> Charles I</b></em> of<em><b> Spain</b></em>) Page 11", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Jesse Buel edited the primary newspaper of this group. The man who coined the name of this group claimed he \u201chad never known a body of men who possessed so much power and used it so well.\u201d Azariah Flagg served as Comptroller of the state in which this group was located. This group fell apart after (+) William Marcy lost an election to William Seward. Thurlow Weed coined the name for this group, one of whom would face the (*)</b> Panic of 1837 as president. For ten points, Martin van Buren was a member of what group that dominated New York state politics in the early nineteenth century?", "answer": "<em><b> Albany Regency</b></em> (prompt on \u201cHoly Alliance\u201d) ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man mailed letters endorsing members of his coalition during a victorious election, known as the \u201ccoupon election.\u201d In one speech this man claimed \u201ca fully-equipped duke costs as much to keep up as two Dreadnoughts.\u201d That sentiment was demonstrated when, as (+) Chancellor of the Exchequer, this man advocated for the passage of increased taxes on the wealthy as part of the People\u2019s Budget. This successor of H.H. Asquith acknowledged that the Battle of (*)</b> Ypres [EEP-ruh] was \u201cone of the great disasters\u201d of its time. For ten points, name this prime minister who led the United Kingdom during World War One.", "answer": "David<em><b> Lloyd George</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}